<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Inspired IT - Moments</title>
    <link>https://inspired-it.nl/moments</link>
    <description>Quick thoughts, observations, and links from Jeroen Gordijn</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 20:04:48 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://inspired-it.nl/moments-rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

  <item>
    <title>February 9, 2026</title>
    <link>https://inspired-it.nl/moments#2026-02-09</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://inspired-it.nl/moments#2026-02-09</guid>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://pi.dev">Pi</a> is such a cool project. It makes me think in whole other ways about working with LLMs. No more magice, all logic is put in place by me. I still like <a href="https://opencode.ai">OpenCode</a> as well. But using Pi I now better understand what’s happening.</p>
<hr>
<p>AI may make you more productive, but working more and more… I’m not alone: <a href="https://x.com/simonw/status/2020901645597683870?s=46">https://x.com/simonw/status/2020901645597683870?s=46</a></p>
<hr>
<p>This shows the power of <a href="https://pi.dev">Pi</a>, if you can imagine it, you can build it: <a href="https://github.com/nicobailon/pi-prompt-template-model">https://github.com/nicobailon/pi-prompt-template-model</a></p>
<hr>
<p>Building a little bot for slack with AI using Claude Opus 4.6. Without asking, it builds integration with OpenAI’s API. Why didn’t it favor Claude SDK? Now that I switch to OpenRouter it becomes apparent that OpenRouter and Ollama are all using the OpenAI API, so I think OpenAI API is just more common.</p>
<hr>
<p>Just set up a Slack bot in about 1h to add messages to my moments (<a href="https://github.com/jgordijn/moments-slackbot">https://github.com/jgordijn/moments-slackbot</a>). This message was created via Slack. The power we get! An idea is now realized in no time 💪</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In rule form:
• Code <em>must not be</em> written by humans
• Code <em>must not be</em> reviewed by humans
Finally, in practical form:
• If you haven’t spent at least <em>$1,000 on tokens today</em> per human engineer, your software factory has room for improvement</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Nice. No more coding by hand. No more reviewing. Tokens as a measure of effectiveness 😎</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Tests can be reward hacked</em> - we needed validation that was less vulnerable to the model cheating</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Building a digital Twin of services to allow for massive integration testing. Create tests, not accessible by the agents. Instead of a Boolean test, write a probabilistic and empirical one. 🤯</p>
<p>Source: <a href="https://factory.strongdm.ai">https://factory.strongdm.ai</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>February 8, 2026</title>
    <link>https://inspired-it.nl/moments#2026-02-08</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://inspired-it.nl/moments#2026-02-08</guid>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Going to experiment with adding a microblog to the site. The idea is simple: quick notes and observations that don’t need the full treatment of a blog post. Sometimes you just want to jot down a thought. Inspired by the “Moments” section on <a href="https://aishepherd.nl/moments/">aishepherd.nl</a> by Jeroen Dee.</p>
<hr>
<p>How to secure your agent? You can’t. You can try to put some instructions, but if it has bash access, it can just do about everything.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>A huge part of working with agents is discovering their limits. The limits keep moving right now, which means constant re-learning. But if you try some penny-saving cheap model like Sonnet, or a second rate local model, you do worse than waste your time, <em>you learn the wrong lessons</em>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>— <a href="https://crawshaw.io/blog/eight-more-months-of-agents">crawshaw.io</a></p>
<p>Nice hot take. Use the best models before complaining LLMs don’t work.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>